At this time, we will end the first stage of the exam.
現在宣布第一階段考試結束
1ST PARTY TON, METHODE, LÄNGE
（第一小隊，托恩、梅特戴、蓮花）
A total of 18 people in six parties have passed the first stage.
第一階段考試共有6隊18人通過
4TH PARTY LAND, FERN, ÜBEL
（第四小隊，蘭特、費倫、尤蓓爾）
The second stage will be in three days.
三天後進行第二階段考試
13TH PARTY RICHTER, DENKEN, LAUFEN
（第十三小隊 利希塔、鄧肯、拉歐芬）
We will share the details later.
後續會再通知各位考試內容
17TH PARTY BLEI, EDEL, DÜNSTE
（第十七小隊 布萊、艾黛爾、敦斯特）
That is all. You're dismissed.
以上，解散
ORIGINAL STORY BY KANEHITO YAMADA / TSUKASA ABE
（原作：山田鐘人，作畫：阿部司）
It's evening, huh?
已經傍晚了嗎？
Spending a day doing nothing isn't so bad.
一整天無所事事感覺也不賴呢
What?
幹嘛啊？
All right, all right.
來了
Fern! I thought you were taking the first-class mage exam?
費倫，你們不是 去參加一級魔法使測驗嗎？
The first stage ended, so we came back last night.
第一階段結束了 昨天晚上我們就回來了
Master Stark, it's already evening, isn't it?
修塔爾克大人，現在已經傍晚了吧？
Huh?
咦？
You were asleep, weren't you?
你到剛剛都還在睡吧？
Did you stay up late?
熬夜了嗎？
-Yes. -What else?
-對 -還有呢？
I drank juice in the middle of the night.
我半夜喝了果汁
I'm sorry! I said, I'm sorry!
對不起嘛！我都說對不起了嘛！
Look at what you've done. Now she's mad.
你看看你，惹人家生氣了吧？
Mistress Frieren, you yourself just woke up a moment ago.
芙莉蓮大人也是剛剛才起床的吧？
That backfired on me.
被波及了
We'll have to spend the day trying to get on Fern's good side.
看來今天得想辦法哄費倫開心了
What are you planning to do?
所以你打算怎麼做？
Why don't we eat something tasty?
要不要去吃點好吃的？
Something tasty?
好吃的？
It's a little expensive,
雖然有點貴
but I found a nice place when I came here with Himmel and everyone.
但是是家不錯的餐廳 以前跟欣梅爾他們來這裡時發現的
But that's more than 80 years ago, right?
但那是八十多年前的事情了吧？
Does it still exist?
現在還有開嗎？
Oh, the light turned on!
燈亮了！
See? I told you it's easy to fix.
我說過馬上就能修好的吧？
-Thank you as always, Richter. -No problem.
-一直以來麻煩你了，利希塔 -沒什麼
Oh, that reminds me. Take these as well.
對了，請收下這些
Bye now.
那就再見了
Hey, Grandma! I'm not a kid anymore.
喂，婆婆，我已經不是小鬼了
I'm an old man already.
我已經是個上年紀的大叔了
You're still a child in the eyes of an elderly person like me.
在我這樣的老人眼中 你依舊是個小鬼
You used to like those, didn't you?
你不是很喜歡吃那個嗎？
Sorry, but it's closing time already.
抱歉，但我們已經打烊了
Some crazy grandpa forced me into a fistfight.
都是因為某個瘋老頭 逼我跟別人肉搏戰
So I need to get some rest.
所以必須要好好休息一下
Well, I'm sorry to hear that, Richter.
那還真是災難呢，利希塔
In that case, why don't we go out to eat?
那至少一起吃頓飯吧？
There's a restaurant I'm looking for,
我正在找一家餐廳
but Laufen and I don't know our way around here.
但拉歐芬跟我對這裡的路不熟
First of all, Laufen, why are you with Denken?
話說回來，拉歐芬 你怎麼會跟鄧肯在一起？
Where did you get that thing you're eating?
你嘴裡吃的又是在哪裡買的？
The old man bought it for me. I'm not giving you any.
爺爺買給我的，我才不分你吃
Jeez, he's treating you like his grandchild!
什麼啊，簡直變成他孫女了嘛！
Go away. We're not in the same party anymore.
回去吧，我們已經不是隊友了
You really don't know how to get on in the world, do you?
你真是不知道如何待人處世吧？
If you want to live as a mage,
想作為魔法使活下去的話
it wouldn't hurt to get on my good side.
討好一下老夫不會吃虧的
There are a ton of restaurants out there.
餐廳的話到處都有
Go pick a random one.
隨便找一家就行了
My wife…
我妻子…
When she was still alive, my wife and I went to this restaurant.
她還在世的時候 我們曾去過一家餐廳
What we ate there was unforgettable.
在那裡嚐到的味道實在讓人難以忘懷
You're paying, right?
是你請客吧？
Of course.
當然
I told you, "It won't hurt."
我說了，你不會吃虧的
-Four-eyes. -Huh?
-眼鏡男 -幹嘛？
Übel.
尤蓓爾
It's my first time meeting you.
這是第一次見到你呢
I see you don't use your clone around town.
在城裡你果然不用分身呢
If you just want to chat, can we keep walking?
只是想聊個天的話 可以邊走邊聊吧？
That's fine,
沒什麼不行的
but if you run away, I might accidentally kill you.
但你要是逃走的話 我可能一不小心就會殺了你喔
Can I ask you a question?
可以問你一個問題嗎？
Huh?
什麼問題？
You…
你這個人啊
think nothing of killing people, right?
其實覺得殺人沒什麼，對吧？
Why didn't you kill Wirbel?
為什麼你沒殺掉威亞貝爾？
You had the chance to kill him.
你明明有機會殺他的
You were watching? I can't let my guard down around you.
你看到了？ 還真是不能對你掉以輕心呢
It's hard to put into words…
雖然難以用言語表達…
How surprising.
真是令人意外
Your hands are stained with blood already,
明明雙手早就沾滿血跡了
but you still wish to be human, huh?
但卻還想好好當個人嗎？
That's right. This is the time I need to find my resolve to kill.
沒錯，這是讓我做好殺人覺悟的時間
I guess it's because I could relate to him.
我想是因為我跟他產生共鳴了吧
It made me want to buy time before I kill too.
我也想要在下殺手前能有猶豫的時間
I can't move my body.
身體動不了了
This is…
這是…
Sorganeil.
將看見的人進行拘禁的魔法
A spell that restrains those within sight.
把視線中的對象束縛住的魔法
The type of magic one specializes in
一個人專精的魔法種類
greatly reflects their life and character.
相當能夠反映出 那個人經歷的人生與性格
I've always been this way.
我從以前就是這樣
When I can relate to people, I am able to use their magic.
只要能跟對方產生共鳴 就能使用對方的魔法
When I can't relate, I can't use their magic.
如果無法產生共鳴 就用不了對方的魔法
Four-eyes, your clone
眼鏡男，你的分身
is a perfect replica of you and functions just like you.
擁有跟本體一模一樣的機能 可謂完美的複製體
What goes on in your mind
你到底在想些什麼？
and what kind of life have you led?
又是過著怎樣的人生？
Tell me.
告訴我吧
I see…
原來如此
So you're the type who uses magic intuitively, huh?
所以你是靠感覺來用魔法的類型啊？
The type who uses a spell without even understanding
是那種不知道背後原理
its mechanisms.
就能使用魔法的類型
You know, I hate those kinds of empty-headed people.
我討厭那些沒大腦的人
You didn't answer my question.
你還沒回答我的問題
What I'm trying to say is, "I don't like you, so I won't tell you."
我想說的就是 “我不爽你這個人，所以無可奉告”
Feel free to kill me if you want.
想殺我的話，你請便
Although, if you do, you'd never be able to relate to me.
只不過你不會 再有機會跟我產生共鳴了
No, I won't kill you.
不用，我不會殺你
I think I got the gist of the kind of person you are.
我覺得我大概知道你是哪種人了
Is that so?
是嗎？
I think I want to know more.
我還想多認識你一點
Where were you headed?
你要去哪裡？
Who knows? Don't follow me.
誰知道？別跟著我
This is it.
就是這裡
You have a good eye, Denken.
眼光真不錯呢，鄧肯
This is the best restaurant in this town.
這是城裡最好的餐廳
I come here a lot.
我也常常來這裡吃飯
It's already been 50 years since the time my wife and I came here,
上次跟我妻子來這裡用餐 已經是五十年前的事了
but it still has the same atmosphere.
竟然還留有當時的氛圍
How strange is that.
真是不可思議
Are you sure?
真的嗎？
Are you sure I can order as many desserts as I want?
真的我想吃多少點心就點多少嗎？
Go ahead.
可以
Denken, it's Frieren.
鄧肯，是芙莉蓮
What should I order?
該點什麼好呢？
I recommend…
我推薦你…
I'm allowed such a luxury even though it's not my birthday?
明明不是生日，可以這樣奢侈嗎？
Let them be.
隨他們去吧
They look like they're enjoying themselves.
看起來他們很開心
Dining is meant to be enjoyable.
吃飯就是該高高興興的
And that's what we're here to do.
吾等也是為了開心用餐才來的
All right, time to stuff myself.
好，準備飽餐一頓囉
That's a crazy amount of food.
也吃太多了吧
Every once in a while, Mistress Frieren eats like this.
芙莉蓮大人偶爾會這麼吃
Thank you for retrieving this knife, our family heirloom,
感謝各位從魔族那裡取回了
from the demons.
我的家傳寶刀
I, Lecker, the greatest chef of the century,
本世紀最強廚師，在下列卡
will show you my utmost hospitality
就為各位獻上最大的誠意
and reward you as much as possible.
盡可能招待各位作為報酬吧
That's quite a lot of food you have.
你吃的份量真不少呢
The food here is delicious, so I have to enjoy it as much as I can.
這裡的東西很好吃 所以要盡量多吃點啊
You don't have to eat so much at once.
不用一次吃那麼多啊
Just come back again.
之後再來光顧就好了
There are so many things that I never got to eat again because of that mentality.
就是因為抱持那種想法 很多東西就再也吃不到了
There is no need to worry, Mistress Frieren.
放心吧，芙莉蓮大人
I plan to pass down our restaurant's recipe for many generations.
我打算讓本店的味道代代傳承下去
Whether that is 100 or 200 years from now.
不管是一百年後或是兩百年後
I see. I find it interesting that chef's always say that.
這樣啊，還真是有趣 料理人都是這麼說的
But despite saying that,
話是這麼說
they also change recipes of old dishes to leave a mark in history.
每個人還是會改變過去的料理 好能留下自己的痕跡
When they do that, just go look for something more delicious.
到那個時候 再去找更好吃的料理就好了
Excuse me, Master Himmel,
那倒未必，欣梅爾大人
but nobody in this world can surpass my cooking.
在這世上沒有人能超越我的料理
Then you must make sure to pass it on to the future.
那麼請你務必讓這個味道流傳到後世
That is the reward I demand from you this time.
這就是我向你索取的報酬了
If that is our hero's request,
既然是我們勇者大人的請託
I will make sure to accomplish this feat which no other chef
我一定會做出其他廚師
has ever accomplished.
都沒做到的豐功偉業
Frieren! This tastes so good!
芙莉蓮，這真的超級好吃！
Is it okay for me to be this happy?
我真的可以這麼幸福嗎？
Jeez…
什麼嘛
After all that he said, the flavor did change in the end.
說了那麼多大話 最後味道還是改變了
But…
不過…
I don't have to go looking for something more delicious.
倒是不用再去找更好吃的東西
This tastes even better than back then.
這個味道比以前的還要好吃
This is really delicious.
真的好好吃喔
You've got some on your cheek, Master Stark.
臉上沾到食物了，修塔爾克大人
You've got to eat your vegetables too.
青菜也要吃才行啊
You're literally becoming her grandpa.
你完全變成她爺爺了嘛
You're a surprisingly light eater.
你吃的還真簡單
Mind your own business.
你少管閒事
That was delicious, Mistress Frieren.
真是好吃呢，芙莉蓮大人
I'm glad she's in a good mood now.
她心情不錯，真是太好了
By the way, did you have enough money?
話說回來，你存的錢夠付嗎？
I used all the money I saved up.
私房錢全花光了
That is indeed, the state of nothingness.
到此這就是無之境界了
I commend you for discovering the quintessence of strength.
恭喜你領悟了武學真諦
There is nothing left for me to teach you.
我已經沒有什麼可教你的了
Who is that old man?
那個老爺爺是誰啊？
Some stranger.
不認識的人
He starts talking to me whenever I'm training.
只要我在修行，他就會找我說話
You always attract the weirdest people.
你總是吸引奇怪的人靠近呢
Well, whatever. Do you have a moment?
不管那個了，你有空嗎？
I could use your help.
我需要你的幫忙
What happened?
怎麼了？
What? She's super angry.
咦？她超生氣的
Her mood is worse than yesterday.
這不是比昨天還糟糕嘛
Yeah…
是啊
What did you do?
你做什麼事了？
I was in charge of shopping today, but I overslept.
今天我負責採買，但我睡過頭了
But that happens all the time.
你平常不也都睡過頭嘛
Why is this time different?
怎麼這次就不一樣？
Fern is the type that bottles up her frustration until it explodes.
費倫是那種會累積怒火 然後一次爆發的類型啊
What happens when it explodes?
爆發的話會怎樣？
She stops talking to me.
就不跟我說話了
What a childish way of fighting.
你們是小孩子吵架啊？
Please, Stark!
拜託你，修塔爾克！
Be our mediator. She won't speak to me.
幫我們調解一下，她不會跟我說話的
What? No way! She's scary!
什麼？才不要！她很恐怖耶！
You're right.
說得也是
Sorry for asking you such a thing.
勉強你了，真是抱歉
Um, Fern,
那個，費倫啊
as you can see, she seems to be repentant.
你看嘛，她都已經在反省了
-I want to eat… -Huh?
-我想吃… -什麼？
I want to eat a snack.
我想吃點心
She's such a pain.
這個人好麻煩
Well then, let's all go buy it together.
那麼，大家一起去買吧
Did I have any more of my savings left?
我的私房錢還有剩嗎？
Hey, that guy…
咦？那傢伙…
Isn't he Wirbel from the Northern Magic Corps?
那不是北部魔法隊的威亞貝爾嗎？
You're a warrior, aren't you?
你是戰士吧？
Huh? What is this about?
咦？有什麼事嗎？
What do you think?
怎麼樣？
Huh? What?
咦？幹嘛？
This guy is no good.
這傢伙不行
What is he doing?
他在幹什麼啊？
Sorry for the wait, Kanne.
抱歉讓你久等了，康涅
You're dressed cuter than usual, Lawine.
你穿得比平常還可愛耶，拉比涅
My older brothers are back from the Imperial Capital.
因為哥哥們從帝都回來了
They keep buying me useless things.
他們老是買一些沒用的東西給我
I'm not a dress-up doll, for crying out loud.
真是的，我又不是換裝娃娃
Mom was enjoying it just as much and didn't stop them at all.
母親自己也很喜歡 所以根本不會阻止他們
You're more spoiled than me.
你比我還要受到寵愛呢
If you think so, I'd gladly trade places with you.
你真的這麼想的話 我很樂意跟你交換身分
Always being compared with your capable brothers is a nightmare.
老是被拿去跟能幹的哥哥們比較 簡直就像活在地獄裡
Come on, let's go. I need to get some fresh air.
好了，我們走吧，我得去喘口氣
All right, then I will escort you today, Lawine.
那麼今天就由我 來當你的護花使者，拉比涅
Ouch! You're ripping my hair out!
好痛啊，要扯掉了啦！
Um, Fern?
那個，費倫…
Which one would you like?
你喜歡哪個？
Anything is fine. Master Stark, you can choose.
哪個都好，修塔爾克大人，你選就好
That usually means she won't be happy with anything.
通常這反應就表示她哪種都不會滿意
What should I do?
怎麼辦啊？
Don't ask me. I don't know.
你問我，我也不知道啊
-Isn't that Frieren? -Yeah.
-那不是芙莉蓮嗎？ -對
What great timing!
真是剛好！
We were just thinking about visiting your inn.
我們正想去你們下榻的旅店找你們
Who are they?
她們是誰啊？
We were in the same party during the first stage of the exam.
第一階段考試跟我同隊的成員
Frieren really helped us out a lot!
話說，芙莉蓮真的幫了我們很多忙
She was also like a teacher to us.
還有啊，她就像個老師一樣
Only because you're always fighting.
那是因為你們倆總是在吵架
That's Lawine's fault.
那都是拉比涅的錯
I feel so out of place amongst all these girls.
身邊都是女孩子，感覺好不自在
Now, now…
算了…
-Hey! -Huh?
-喂！ -咦？
You're a warrior, right?
你是戰士吧？
What? Hey.
什麼？等等
Hey, stop. What are you doing?
喂，住手，這是在幹嘛？
You're really great.
你真的很不錯呢
What is going on?
這是怎樣啦？
The Continental Magic Association
大陸魔法協會
asked us to get rid of a fresser that's been ruining the crops.
委託我們去除掉破壞作物的獅子豬
So I'm looking for a vanguard.
所以我正在找前衛
We met during the exam, right?
我們考試時見過面吧？
Is he your friend? Can I borrow him?
他是你的同伴嗎？能借我嗎？
-Go ahead. -How ruthless!
-你請便 -好過分！
-So ruthless… -They're taking him away. Is that okay?
-好過分… -他被帶走了，不要緊嗎？
I'm sure it's fine.
沒事的
I didn't sense any malicious intent.
我沒有感覺到對方有不良企圖
I almost didn't recognize him.
無法想像跟之前那位是同一個人
He must be the type who changes once he's in "work mode."
他一定是那種工作模式上身 就換了一個人的傢伙吧
My brothers are the same way.
我哥哥他們就是這樣
Here, Frieren. This is a thank you gift.
給你，芙莉蓮，這是謝禮
I didn't do anything to deserve this.
我沒做什麼值得謝禮的事情啊
No, if we didn't have you,
不，如果沒有你的話
we wouldn't have made it to the second stage.
我們不可能進到第二階段
Thank you.
謝謝你
Master Himmel!
欣梅爾大人！
-There's no need to worry anymore. -Okay.
-以後就不用擔心了 -嗯
Well then, don't keep your mom and dad waiting.
好了，別讓爸媽等你太久
Okay!
好！
Why do you help people, Himmel?
欣梅爾，你為什麼要幫助別人呢？
Because I'm a hero.
因為我是勇者啊
That's not what I mean.
我不是那個意思
Well…
說得也是呢
I might be doing it for myself.
也許，這麼做是為了我自己吧
Maybe it's because I want
也許是因為我想要被其他人
to be remembered by others, even if it's just a little.
記住自己的事，就算只有一點點也好
Being alive means being known and remembered by someone.
活著這件事就要為人熟知並且記住啊
What can you do to be remembered?
要怎麼做才能被記住呢？
Even if it's very subtle, just try to change someone's life.
就算是很細微的小事 試著去改變別人的人生吧
I'm sure that's all it takes.
做到這一點就夠了
And that's when Lawine…
拉比涅那時候就…
No, that was you, Kanne.
才不是呢，那是你，康涅
Oh, was it?
是嗎？
Remember that other time?
你還記得那時候嗎？
That's right!
對耶！
Mistress Frieren, these snacks that they brought are so good.
芙莉蓮大人 她們帶來的餅乾好好吃喔
She's finally in a good mood.
她心情總算變好了
That reminds me…
說起來，芙莉蓮
You took forever to wake up on the second day.
你第二天早上還真是能賴床呢
Don't bring that topic up. She'll get mad again.
不要提這個了，不然她又要生氣了
Pout…
真是…
Frieren,
芙莉蓮
if they're doing it like usual, the exam will go to a third stage.
按往年考試情形來看 應該會有第三階段
We'll be enemies from now on.
下次考試我們就是敵人了
Yeah.
是啊
What's this?
這是什麼？
It's the notice for the next stage.
是下一階段考試的通知
It has the venue, date and time,
上面寫明了地點、日期跟時間
and name of the proctor for the second stage.
還有第二階段監考官的姓名
The proctor is Sense, huh? We're out of luck…
監考官是冉則？還真是倒楣
We passed the first stage for nothing.
好不容易才通過第一階段的
What do you mean?
什麼意思？
Sense has been a proctor four times in the past.
冉則過去曾四度擔任監考官
Each time, zero examinees passed.
每次都沒有考生合格
This meat tastes great!
好好吃的肉啊！
You're amazing! I witnessed the quintessence of strength.
你真厲害，我見識到武學的真諦了
What a horrible exam.
真是過分的測驗內容
You think so?
是嗎？
I am a pacifist.
我是和平主義者
Unlike you, Genau.
跟葛納烏你不同
-Who knew we'd find this. -Gargoyles!
-誰知道會找到這個 -石像鬼！
-It's a mimic. -This is sick.
-是仿製品 -有病
-That's not possible. -It must be that.
-那不可能 -一定是那樣
A demon or monster.
魔族或魔物
-That will be very dangerous. -Let's proceed with caution.
-那會非常危險 -小心行事
"Conquering the Labyrinth."
《攻略迷宮》
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻譯：洪貞韻